INVENTORY TO THE PIERCE FAMILY PAPERS, 1841-1940 D-022
University of California, Davis General Library, Dept. of Special Collections
- Pierce Family, 1852-1928; Series 7.; 0.5 ln. ft., 68 items
  - Printed Material, 1852-1928; Subseries 7.3.; 61 items
    - Pamphlets, 1852-1928; 7 items
      - "That Crime of '73," San Francisco, CA: Spaulding, George and Company, ca., 1895; 1 item (Box 8, Folder 62)
      - Van Dyke, H., "The Battle of Life," New York: Crowell, Thomas Y. and Company, Pamphlet and envelope., 1907; 2 items (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Poem (typed); "Fourth O' July," n.d., 1 item (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Postcards, n.d., 2 items (Box 8, Folder 65.1)
    - Programs, n.d., 1879-1916; 3 items (Box 8, Folder 65.2)
    - Raffle Ticket, ca., 1916; 1 item (Box 8, Folder 65.3)
    - Schedules; California Pacific Railroad and Steamer New World, 1870; 3 items (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Sheet Music, n.d., 2 items (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Student Publication; "The Netherlands," Rio Vista, CA: Rio Vista High School,., 1915; 1 item (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Artifacts, n.d., Subseries 7.4.; 2 items
    - Checkbooks (empty), n.d., 2 items (Box 8, Folder 69)
- Photographs, 1875-1929; Series 8.; 1 ln. ft., 131 items
  Series VIII., Photographs (ca. 1875-1929), contains 131 items and takes up 1 linear foot of space in an archives box and a document case. 127 black and white prints, 1 negative, 1 program, and 2 postcards are included in the Photographs series. All dimensions of prints and frames are given in inches.
  If a notation was made on the back of a photograph, it was used as the photograph description and has been enclosed in quotation marks.
  The acidic gray cardboard frames were removed from the first 11 photographs (all by the photographer Morton) in the photographs series but everything that was written on the back of the frames was preserved in the photograph descriptions.
  In general, the larger prints (most often 8x10) and the cabinet card photographs have been made by professional California photographers such as Morton, McCurry Foto Company, Lother and Young Studios, Morse's Palace of Art, Webster, Alice M. Wilson, J. W. Bird of Globe Portrait Company, Kilborn, Taber, and Hodson Photo. Smaller prints may be snapshots taken by George W. Pierce, Jr., Pierce Family members, or acquaintences. Many of the snapshots feature the Kodak Company name. Some photographs of almond trees were made by the United States, Department of Agriculture.
  The photographs in Series VIII throw light on the activities especially of George W. Pierce, Jr. but also of other Pierce Family members. This series is divided by subject into 4 subseries: California Almond Growers' Exchange, Sacramento Valley, University of California, and Other.
  Although not part of the Pierce Family Papers, an interesting photograph of George W. Pierce, Sr. and other Davisville, CA founding fathers can be found in the Warren A. Westgate Collection of photographs at the University of California, Davis, General Library, Special Collections Department.
  - California Almond Growers' Exchange, n.d., 1919-1923; Subseries 8.1.; 31 items
    A subseries of the Photographs series, many of the California Almond Growers' Exchange (C. A. G. E.) prints (circa 1920) are of the rooms and display cases in the Exchange's headquarters offices in San Francisco, CA. Other C. A. G. E. photographs were made in various locations such as the Sacramento, CA plant or the Lodi, CA warehouse and feature important political figures along with the leaders of C. A. G. E. For example, Senator Hiram W. Johnson posed with C. A. G. E. president George W. Pierce, Jr. while at the Sacramento plant. In addition, the C. A. G. E. subseries includes 11 halftone prints (photo A-21) of Spanish almond orchards and laborers. These images were used in the 1921 C. A. G. E. pamphlet, "Shall the American Almond Industry Perish?"
    Diary entries made by George W. Pierce, Jr. can sometimes be matched to dated photographs. For example, photo A-18 of the Lodi warehouse must be related to Pierce's August 1, 1919 diary entry: "Went to Sacto., met Tucker at Hotel Sacramento--took Schmitt's machine and the three of us drove to Lodi--stopping at plant...went to Lodi plant--saw rig run...lunched at Lodi Hotel--went to see Messrs. Stephens, Ryan, and Marshall." Also, photo A-19, "Golden Gate Park, Mr. Hoyt of Oklahoma, Pierce," matches Pierce's July 26, 1919 diary entry which states: "Went to Palace Hotel with Mr. and Mrs. Tucker--met Mr. __of Kansas City and Mrs. Hoyt of Oklahoma. Mrs. H. met Mr. Hoyt and Mr. __ whose guests we were for luncheon."
    - Photo A-1, "California and Battery Sts., San Francisco, No. 311 California St.-Offices of California Almond Growers' Exchange on Third Floor," Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Photo A-2, Almond display at San Francisco, CA offices, Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Photo A-3, "Display case in office," San Francisco, CA, Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Photo A-4, "Display case at entrance to offices," San Francisco, CA, Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Photo A-5, "Office Hall," San Francisco, CA, Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Photo A-6, "Reception Room," San Francisco, CA, Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Photo A-7, "Managers Office," San Francisco, CA, Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Photo A-8, "Accounting room," San Francisco, CA, Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Photo A-9, Office with desks and office machinery, San Francisco, CA, Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Photo A-10, Almond Display, Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Photo A-11, Almond Display, Morton, n.d., 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Photo A-12, "In front of Almond Plant in Sacramento," Left to right: Senator Bills, George W. Pierce, Jr., Senator Hiram W. Johnson, T. C. Tucker, D. R. Bailey, Postmaster McCurrey. Rear: D. S. Wilson. McCurry Foto Company, Sept. 1922; 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Photo A-13, "At almond plant in Sacramento." T. C. Tucker, Senator Hiram W. Johnson, and George W. Pierce, Jr., in center; McCurry Foto Company, Sept. 1922; 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Photo A-14, "Directors of California Almond Growers' Exchange," San Francisco, CA: E. S. Norton, South Butte; A. C. Woodworth, Lodi, CA; G. N. Talbot, Paso Robles; D. S. Nelson, Arbuckle, CA; Harry J. Wood; John Trembarth, Oakley, CA; George W. Pierce, Jr., President, Davis, CA; C. D. Hamilton, Banning, CA; T. C. Tucker, Oakland; James Miles, Hamilton City, CA. Lother and Young Studios of San Francisco, CA, May 4, 1923; 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Photo A-15, "Board of Directors and Manager of California Almond Growers' Exchange": A. R. Stephen, Lodi, CA; Manger, T. C. Tucker; C. D. Hamilton; V. C. Richards, Chico, CA; George W. Pierce, Jr., Davis, CA; E. S. Norton, Sutter County, CA. Lother and Young Studios of San Francisco, CA, April 1923; 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Photo A-16, "Eight members of the Board of Directors of the California Almond Growers' Exchange: its manager; and Mrs. James Mills, wife of Director Mills; Prof. Taylor, horticulturist; and D. R. Bailey, Superintendent of the Sacramento plant. Picture taken in front of the Sacto. Plant." McCurry Foto Company, Dec. 12, 1923; 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Photo A-17. George W. Pierce, Jr., President, California Almond Growers' Exchange; T. C. Tucker, Manager. Lother and Young Studios of San Francisco, CA, April 1923; 1 print; 8x10 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Photo A-18, "Lodi warehouse; Pierce, Cunningham, Schmitt,", July 1919; 1 print; 4.75x3.75 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Photo A-19, "Golden Gate Park, Mr. Hoyt of Oklahoma, Pierce,", July 1919; 1 print; 4.75x3.75 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Photo A-20, "Martinette, Pierce, Herman, in front of The Park Hotel," Chico, CA, June 15, 1919; 1 print; 6x8 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Photo A-21. Images of almond orchards used in creating the California Almond Growers' Exchange pamphlet, "Shall the American Almond Industry Perish?" n.d., halftone prints., 11 prints; 5x5 images printed on 7x11 paper (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Sacramento Valley, n.d., 1866-1919; Subseries 8.2.; 39 items
    A part of the Photographs series, the Sacramento Valley subseries consists of photographs taken on the Pierce Ranch and at various other Valley locations.
    Those photographs taken on the Pierce Ranch show such activities as prune dipping, sheep dipping, and harvesting crops. Many types of agricultural technology are evident in the Ranch photographs, and researchers interested in almond orchards can find images of almond trees and almond harvesting activities (including a shot of Chinese laborers "knocking" almonds) here.
    Photographs taken at various locations in the Sacramento Valley include images of farm machinery in use, Yolo County, CA roads, the Sacramento River, and the Yolo County exhibit for the 1907 California State Fair. Photo B-2-c, "Dixwell beside the new Balfour scale house in Davis..." has been alternately identified in John Lofland's and Phyllis Haig's book, "Images of America: Davis, CA, 1910s-1940s," as the "Grain Scale House of Plant's Grain Warehouse at Fifth and G," in Davis, CA.
    The date that 2 prints and a negative (photo B-2-i) were made of a Nov. 27, 1866 broadside is unknown.
    - On the Pierce Ranch, 1878-1919; Subseries 8.2.1.; 28 items
      - Photo B-1-a, Susan Gilmore Pierce and son, Kodak, 1900; 1 print; 3.75x4.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 22)
      - Photo B-1-b, "Prune dipping on Pierce Ranch," Kodak, 1901; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 23)
      - Photo B-1-c, "Prune dipping--Pierce Ranch," Kodak, 1901; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Photo B-1-d, "Wool from Pierce Ranch," Kodak, ca., 1900-1915; 1 print; 3.75x4.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 25)
      - Photo B-1-e, "Sheep dipping--Pierce Place," Kodak, ca., print., 1900-1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 26)
      - Photo B-1-f, "Sheep-dipping, Pierce Ranch," Kodak, ca., 1900-1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 prints on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 27)
      - Photo B-1-g, "Sheep dipping--Pierce Ranch," Kodak, ca., 1900-1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 prints on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 28)
      - Photo B-1-h, "Pierce header with derrick unloading device for header wagons." Pictured are: M. Connell, P. Stripe, J. Hartigan, C A. Gibson, J. Deomezio, I. Lafswell, and V. Zanini., 1878; 1 print; 7.75x4.75 print on 8x5 board (Box 9, Folder 29)
      - Photo B-1-i, Harvester, Best Manufacturing Company, Pierce Ranch, 1891; 1 print; 5.5x8 print on 9x11 board (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Photo B-1-j, "Pierce Harvester," Kodak, 1901; 1 print; 3.5x4.75 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 30)
      - Photo B-1-k, "Pierce Harvester," Kodak, 1901; 1 print; 3.5x4.75 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 31)
      - Photo B-1-l, "Pierce orchard, end tree, 8th row from NE corner, east orchard,", [1919]; 1 print; 4.5x6.5 (Box 9, Folder 32.1)
      - Photo B-1-m, "Almond, soft shell bitter. At head of small orchard N of residence," George W. Pierce, Jr., Davis, CA; United States, Department of Agriculture, Sept. 12, 1919; 1 print; 5x7 (Box 9, Folder 32.2)
      - Photo B-1-n, "Almond hardshell sweet (seed). End tree, east side, 8th row from N.E. Cor. Orchard opposite residence," George W. Pierce, Jr.; United States, Department of Agriculture, Sept. 12, 1919; 1 print; 5x7 (Box 9, Folder 33.1)
      - Photo B-1-o, "Seed, Hardshell sweet, 5th row from east end, 4th row from north side;" George W. Pierce, Jr.; Davis, CA, Sept. 12, 1919; 1 print; 4.5x6.5 (Box 9, Folder 33.2)
      - Photo B-1-p, "Knocking almonds using wagon with sheet attached," Chinese laborers, Kodak, ca., 1900-1915; 1 print; 4x3.5 print on 6.5x5.5 board (Box 9, Folder 34)
      - Photo B-1-q, "Knocking almonds, Pierce Ranch, showing wagon device for sacking," Kodak, ca., 1900-1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 35)
      - Photo B-1-r, "Drying almonds on trays, Pierce Ranch," Kodak, ca., 1900-1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 36)
      - Photo B-1-s, "Drying ground, almond sulphur house, and men's house at drying yard--Pierce place," Kodak, ca., 1900-1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 37)
      - Photo B-1-t, "Packing House, Pierce place," Kodak, ca., 1900-1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 38)
      - Photo B-1-u, "Load of unhulled almonds going from orchard to huller, Pierce ranch," Kodak, ca., 1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 39)
      - Photo B-1-v, "Load of almonds--en route to market--Pierce place," Kodak, ca., 1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 40)
      - Photo B-1-w, "Almonds--en route to market, Pierce ranch," Kodak, ca., 1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 41)
      - Photo B-1-x, "Load of almonds--Pierce place--ready for shipment," Kodak, ca., 1915; 1 print; 4.75x3.5 print on 5.5x6.5 board (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - Various Locations, n.d., 1866-1919; Subseries 8.2.2.; 11 items
      - Photo B-2-a, "Reade Almond Huller," n.d., 1 print; 4x4 print on 5x5.5 board (Box 9, Folder 43)
      - Photo B-2-b, "Spring plowing, J. Currey Farm,", 1884; 1 print; 9x7 print on 9x11 board (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - Photo B-2-c, "Dixwell beside the new Balfour scale house in Davis...Con Hilman in door,", Aug. 8, 1907; 1 print; 5x7 print on 9x11 board (Box 12, Folder 18)
      - Photo B-2-d, "Road scraper (county) on road through to the H. M. Larue and Sons place," Alice M. Wilson of Winters, CA, ca., 1906; 1 print; 6.75x5 print on 9x7 board (Box 12, Folder 19)
      - Photo B-2-e, "State Highway west of Davis, LaRue residence on right,", Sept. 12, 1919; 1 print; 5x7 (Box 9, Folder 44)
      - Photo B-2-f, "Abutment of easement near Elkhorn, Sacramento River. Gardy and I went on the river excursion." J. W. Bird of Globe Portrait Company of Sacramento, CA., Nov. 26, 1898; 1 print; 8.5 print on 10.5 board (Box 12, Folder 20)
      - Photo B-2-g, "Easement, 2 1/2 miles above Elkhorn on Sacramento River, 2000 feet long. Gardner and I went on the river excursion." J. W. Bird of Globe Portrait Company of Sacramento, CA, Nov. 26, 1898; 1 print; 6x8 print on 8.5x10.5 board (Box 12, Folder 21)
      - Photo B-2-h, Yolo County, CA exhibit for California State Fair. Yolo County Where Everything Grows. Kilborn of Sacramento, CA, 1907; 1 print; 6x8 print on 11x14 board (Box 12, Folder 22)
      - Photo B-2-i, Administrator's Sale! Public Notice! Estate of A. Currie sold by George W. Pierce, Sr., Public Administrator of Yolo County, CA; negative and 2 prints of, Nov. 27, 1866; [2 prints, 1 negative]; 11x14 Broadside (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - University of California, n.d., 1875-1915; Subseries 8.3.; 53 items
    University of California is the third subseries within the Photographs series. Late nineteenth and early twentieth century photographs of students, professors, and buildings at the Berkeley, CA campus make up the University of California subseries. An especially notable item held in this subseries is the 1875 class album of George W. Pierce, Jr. It features 42 Morse's Palace of Art cabinet card photographs. The cabinet cards are 6x4 inch portraits of professors and students (including a portrait of Pierce himself). Also part of the album are 4 prints of buildings and a class reunion program (1915). Another cabinet card photograph in the University of California subseries shows the 1894-1895 University of California, Glee Club and lists the members names on the reverse.
    - Photo C-1, Class of Photograph Album, ca., 46 cabinet card photographs and program ()., 1875 1875 1915; 47 items (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Photo C-2, Prof. Hesse; Morse's Palace of Art, San Francisco, CA; n.d., 1 cabinet card photograph; 6.5x4 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Photo C-3; University of California, Glee Club,; Webster of Oakland, 1894-1895 Jan. 10, 1895; 1 cabinet card photograph; 6.5x4 (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Photo C-4, South Hall, Berkeley campus, n.d., 1 print; 7x9 (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Photo C-5, North Hall, Berkeley Campus, n.d., 1 print; 7x9 (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Photo C-6, Mining Building, Jan. 1908; 1 print; 3x4 print on 5x6.5 board (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Photo C-7, Greek Theatre, Jan. 1908; 1 print; 3x4 print on 5x6.5 board (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Other, n.d., 1891-1929; Subseries 8.4.; 8 items
    The fourth subseries of the Photographs series is titled, Other. The subject matter of the 6 photographs and 2 postcards in the Other subseries touches on the 1929 world cruise taken by George W. Pierce, Jr., California boosters, and the California State Assembly, among other things. The photograph (photo D-2) of Pierce riding an elephant at Kandy, Ceylon was originally kept between pages describing Ceylon in Pierce's 1928-1929 Canadian Pacific world cruise diary. Also, photographed during this world cruise and printed on board the Canadian Pacific steamship, Empress of Australia, is (photo D-1) the unidentified image of man, dogs, and cart filled with lumber. Possibly while he was overseas, George W. Pierce, Jr. acquired the print of W. E. Gladstone (photo D-3). Accompanying Gladstone's photograph are 2 color postcards--one of Harwarden Castle (Gladstone's home) and one of Holyrood Chapel in Edinburgh, Scotland. Photo D-4 (the delegation sent from Northern California to get data relative to possibilities of the proposed Southern California branch of the 1915 Panama-Pacific International Exposition) shows the delegation, including George W. Pierce, Jr., posing in the patio Ramona's Marriage Place at San Diego, CA.
    - Photo D-1; Unidentified image of man, dogs, and lumber-filled cart; ca., 1929; 1 print; 6.75x4.75 (Box 12, Folder 30.1)
    - Photo D-2; George W. Pierce, Jr. riding an elephant at Kandy, Ceylon, 1929; 1 print; 3x5 print (Box 12, Folder 30.2)
    - Photo D-3; W. E. Gladstone seated in his garden; McKenzie of Dunkeld; n.d.; matted print and postcards., 1 print, 2 postcards; 9x6 (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - Photo D-4; "Delegation sent from Northern California to get data relative to possibilities of the proposed Southern California branch of the Panama-Pacific, 1915 Exposition...;" San Diego, CA, Sept. 6, 1912; 1 print; 8x10 (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Photo D-5; Warren Olney [(1841-1921)]; Taber of San Francisco, CA, March 1891; 1 cabinet card photograph; 6.5x4 (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Photo D-6; United States Senator, Thomas R. Bard, and members of the California Legislature by whom he was elected; Hodson Photo of Sacramento, CA; ca., 1900; 1 print; 8x10 print on 12x15 board (Box 12, Folder 34)